Software Engineering Manager

Rob Bednark

33 Spinosa Lake Oswego, OR 97035

971-276-8789 <u>rbednark@gmail.com</u> https://www.linkedin.com/in/robbednark

Profile

With 4 years of experience as a software engineering manager, 3 years as a team lead, and 17 years as a software engineer, I have learned to focus on solutions, and meet challenges head-on with empathy and compassion, playing the roles of strategist, leader, engineer, and coach. I'm down to earth, practical, and pragmatic, bringing ideas out of the clouds and into concrete goals and plans. I believe people-centered work cultures increase employee happiness, resulting in more productive, creative, and sustainable workplaces, and that human interaction (listening, collaborating, encouraging, conflict-resolution, ...) is essential.

Technical Skills

Languages (recent) Python, JavaScript, Ruby

Databases DynamoDB, ElasticSearch, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Redis, Solr/Lucene

Tools, Frameworks, Services Amazon

API-Gateway/AWS/DynamoDB/EC2/Lambda/S3/SES, BuildKite, Django, Docker, Git, Grafana, GraphQL, Jenkins, Kubernetes, Node, React, Rails

Methodologies agile, CI/CD, DevOps, kanban, microservices, MVC, OO, scrum, TDD

Operating Systems Linux, macOS, Windows

Experience

Invoca / Software Engineering Manager

Mar 2021 - Aug 2023 Fully remote

I managed a full-stack development team of 5 direct reports responsible for adding new features and maintaining several functional areas of the platform. My responsibilities included:

- Managing direct reports: hiring and determining promotions and raises, weekly 1:1s, quarterly performance reviews, setting expectations and addressing performance issues, conflict resolution, personal development plans, managing interns
- Project management: coordinating with architects, product managers, lead developers, and UX designers to plan and deliver projects; keeping the team focused; assigning roles; mitigating risk and delays; creating plans-of-action; creating roadmaps (features and technical initiatives)
- **Technical**: 24/7 on-call duty; diagnosing issues; coding; reviewing requirements, UX and technical designs; code reviews
- Technology stack: Ruby on Rails, React, Graphql, Apollo, MySQL, Kubernetes, Redis, Kafka, Grafana, Kibana, BuildKite, AWS

Rob Bednark 2

Sabbatical

Feb 2020 - Dec 2020

After Moovel announced they are shutting down, I chose to take a sabbatical to spend time with family and friends, reflect, establish healthy daily habits (meditating, co-learning, co-working, running, journaling, waking early, stretching), learn new technologies, work on apps, and discover activities that I enjoy. I've emerged with increased and renewed self-awareness, health, and relationships, and a renewed sense of purpose and desire for management.

Moovel / Software Engineering Manager, Senior Software Engineer

Nov 2016 - Feb 2020, Portland, OR

As Software Engineering Manager:

 Directly responsible for hiring, employee reviews, coordinating with product managers and account executives, product delivery, 24/7 on-call duty, and team health for two cross-functional development teams of six and seven direct reports.

As Senior Software Engineer:

- Created designs and specifications for new features
- Worked on back-end services (Node, Jenkins, docker, MySQL, Postgres, ElasticSearch, Redis, Splunk, Jenkins, automated testing (unit, functional, integration))
- Worked on a web app for viewing and updating catalog data involving many tables and relationships, using journaling and workflows (React, Redux, html, CSS, JavaScript)

Idealist / Team Lead, Senior Software Engineer

Sep 2015 - Jul 2016, Portland, OR

I worked with 20 other engineers, developing a high-traffic website with over 2 million visits per month with 1 million users and 100k paying customers. Development projects included converting the site to a front-end / RESTful API architecture and implementing an API for external customers to post jobs. Our development environment was extremely collaborative, with extensive pair programming and mob programming.

Technology stack: Python (Flask, SQLAlchemy, RabbitMQ), PostgreSQL, Redis, HAProxy, nginx, gunicorn, Bamboo, Lambda, API Gateway, DynamoDB, Linux.

Trapit / Senior Platform Engineer

Apr 2014 - Aug 2015, Portland, OR

I worked on the multi-tenanted cloud platform, which was responsible for a RESTful API for web and mobile clients; services to continuously pull content from 100k+ RSS feeds into multiple databases; and other services such as sending email and getting social media share analytics. We emphasized performance, scalability, automated testing, and reliability. We had 100k+ RSS feeds, 10k users, 80 enterprise customers, 30 services, and used 100+ PyPI python packages and standard libraries.

Technology stack: AWS, boto S3, Cassandra, fabric, Linux, nginx, NoSQL, ORM, pillow, pipelines, PostgreSQL, puppet, pystache, RabbitMQ, Redis, RSS, SES, Solr / Lucene, SQL, SQLAlchemy, zmq

Rob Bednark 3

Atlatl / Software Architect, Lead Software Engineer

Jan 2013 - Apr 2014, Portland, OR

As employee #10 in a 30-person startup, I was the software architect and team lead for the web application, API's, and database, leading a team of 7 other engineers (3 locally and 4 outsourced in Vietnam). At the time I started there was one other engineer on the team, the software was still in development, and I was actively involved with deploying the project into production for multiple tenants. I championed test automation, code reviews, requirements, architectural designs, configurable features, technical documentation, performance, hiring excellent engineers, automatic test data generation, and logging.

Technology stack: Django, Python, PostgreSQL, Selenium, factory_boy, Linux, Nginx, Memcached, AWS, Sentry, JSON, test-driven development (TDD)

Tixie / Software Engineer

June 2012 - Jan 2013, Portland, OR

I added functionality to the webapp, including user registration and profiles, and created processes to calculate and update data.

Technology stack: Python, Django, Amazon AWS/EC2/S3/SES, Celery, CSS, Fabric, factory_boy, HTML, Linux, Memcached, PostgreSQL, RabbitMQ, Sentry, South, SQL

Uncorked Studios / QA Lead (Contract)

August 2011, Portland, OR

I lead the QA effort for a high-profile iOS, Android, Mobile Web, and web app. Features included Facebook sharing, geocoding, reverse geocoding, geotagging, 2D/3D virtual-reality mapping; upload, display, and playback of video, audio, photo, and text.

Huawei / QA Manager (Contract)

Dec 2010 - July 2011, Portland, OR

I managed the QA of a social-networking web app and mobile apps with VoIP, chat, email, and address book features. I managed the test team; recruited and hired; wrote test plan and testcase specifications; and wrote a web app monitoring tool and automated tests. I worked with a remote team across 13 sites in the U.S., England, Ukraine, Russia, and India. Oversaw test automation utilizing Selenium, Python, nose, Ruby, Capybara, and Cucumber.

The Portland Upside / Founder, Publisher, Editor

October 2008 - May 2010, Portland, OR

I started a print and online monthly newspaper of positive stories. We attracted 200+ volunteers to contribute writing, photography, and to help distribute 9000 printed copies each month. I coordinated and worked on all aspects of the paper, including managing volunteers, finding content, selling advertising, editing, layout, printing, distribution, and website creation and maintenance.

Sabbatical

Nov 2006 - Oct 2008, Portland, OR

Initiated a journalism project where I interviewed 27 people; assisted a friend with a startup; helped my wife self-publish two books. I spent time with my family, soul-searched, and got a lot of rest and relaxation. I came out of the sabbatical rested, with a renewed strong interest in self-awareness, relationships, work, and technology.

Rob Bednark 4

IBM / Software Engineer

July 2001 - Nov 2006, Portland, OR

Independently conceived, architected, and implemented a Python framework for doing distributed, parallel code execution in an environment with an arbitrary number of clients and servers of various platforms. This resulted in a 200% increase in productivity by a team of 10 test engineers writing automated tests, saving the project \$300,000.

Designed and implemented a multi-threaded, multi-process utility to stress-test a file system by randomly reading from millions of files.

Designed, implemented, and supported a "one-button-test" application for 40 engineers to run sanity tests prior to committing, automating all aspects of setup and running of tests, improving main branch reliability.

Informix / Software Engineer

Nov 1996 - July 2001, Portland, OR

Responsible for maintaining over 30 builds and testing of database engines on various platforms, and providing build and version control customer support for engineers. Designed and implemented processes and scripts for all build tasks.

Designed and implemented an online organizational chart web app, making it easy for anyone in the company of 3000+ employees to query or traverse the chart by name, site, team, or business unit.

Milner Technologies / Software Engineer

Sep 1992 - Nov 1996, Minneapolis, MN

Added functionality to existing products, including designing and developing a text editor, a graphics-tablet editor, and redesigning the TCP/IP socket communications component.

Education

St. Cloud State University, St. Cloud, MN – B.S. Computer Science, minor Human Relations, Honors Program, 1992.

Revision: 2023-Oct-4